https://youtu.be/261rMD5B6_Y
.
PAUL CUBBON: I'd like to give you some further insight into some
PAUL CUBBON: Tôi sẽ đi sâu hơn
of the choices you can make.
vào các lựa chọn bạn có
Again, at the strategic level around pricing.
ở cấp độ chiến lược của việc định giá.
We'll get to tactics later.
Ta sẽ nói đến các chiến thuật sau.
So here are some of the things I want you to consider.
Còn giờ thì tôi muốn bạn tập trung vào vấn đề khác.
First of all, the idea of setting your pricing in a tiered manner.
Đầu tiên, về định giá phân hạng.
What do we mean by that?
Bạn hiểu nó như thế nào?
Well, a tiered manner might mean that you're
Phân hạng có nghĩa là
doing a high, medium, and low pricing.
định giá cao, trung bình hoặc thấp cho sản phẩm.
What does that actually look like?
Trông nó ra sao?
Well, sometimes with that we actually see this term freemium that has been
Gần đây mô hình freemium
popularized.
đang rất phổ biến.
And what we're doing really here is we're taking the word free and premium,
Đó là sự kết hợp
and hybridizing it.
giữa miễn phí (free) và cao cấp (premium).
And what we're really saying is that we've got a hybridized pricing model.
Thế là ta có một mô hình định giá kết hợp.
And so low may actually be under here, it may be free.
Cấp độ thấp nhất của nó là miễn phí.
And if you were to take a company like Hootsuite,
Lấy công ty Hootsuite làm ví dụ,
then Hootsuite they clearly offer some of their product for free.
họ cung cấp một số sản phẩm miễn phí.
They have a low monthly subscription fee.
Phí thuê bao tháng của họ khá thấp.
They then have an ability to plug-in to medium pricing with extra add-ons.
Họ có thể định giá trung bình với một số tiện ích thêm vào.
And finally, the high pricing is the custom pricing
Và sau hết, họ định giá cao
for their enterprise clients.
với các khách hàng doanh nghiệp.
And so this idea of tiered pricing means that you can actually
Như vậy, định giá phân hạng có nghĩa là
segment your offerings, and match the right products and services and pricing
phân khúc sản phẩm của bạn rồi định giá sản phẩm, dịch vụ
level, to particular segments that you are deciding to target.
tương ứng với từng phân khúc bạn nhắm đến.
So again we're playing back to some of these earlier themes.
Một lần nữa ta quay lại chủ đề trước đó.
You don't necessarily want to offer one product at one price
Không cần thiết phải ra giá giống nhau cho cùng loại sản phẩm
to all of your different customers.
với đối tượng khách hàng khác nhau.
And so other companies that do this?
Những công ty khác có làm điều này không?
We'll think about mobile gaming apps.
Hãy nghĩ đến những trò chơi trên di động.
You often have something which is free to start with, here.
Bạn sẽ luôn có một điểm bắt đầu, miễn phí, ở đây.
And then you will have maybe a secondary level uprising here, maybe
Sau đó bước lên cấp độ thứ hai ở đây
with some menus of additional virtual products that you can buy.
sẽ có vài vật phẩm ảo mà bạn có thể mua.
And we also see with things like LinkedIn, which many of you
LinkedIn là một ví dụ
should be familiar with.
hết sức quen thuộc.
If you ask yourself, or your colleagues around your office,
Nếu bạn hỏi chính mình, bạn bè hay đồng nghiệp
you'll find that most people go for the free version.
bạn sẽ thấy nhiều người sử dụng bản miễn phí.
But there are others that are paying, and then you
Nhưng cũng có những người trả tiền,
have to start looking at other pricing and revenue
và bạn sẽ nhìn thấy những định giá và dòng doanh thu khác
streams for different customer types in a category like that.
vì đối tượng khách hàng ở đây cũng khác.
It gets a little bit more complicated.
Nghe hơi phức tạp một chút.
So that's tiered pricing, one level that we're going to look at.
Nhưng đó chính là định giá phân hạng.
The second one I want you to consider is dynamic pricing.
Khía cạnh thứ hai mà tôi muốn nói đến là định giá động.
And dynamic pricing-- if you recall, when
Bạn hãy nhớ lại
Darren talked to you about the Coke vending machine
bài giảng của Darren về máy bán Coca
experiment where they change the pricing with the temperature outside-- then
khi công ty này tiến hành chỉnh giá theo nhiệt độ ngoài trời
this was an experiment in changing pricing to changing conditions.
đó là một thí nghiệm về điều chỉnh giá khi điều kiện thay đổi.
So the first one, the tiered pricing, was really changing the pricing
Định giá phân hạng là điều chỉnh giá
based on the product and service changing to match the customer segment.
theo phân khúc khách hàng.
Here we've got the same customer, the same product,
Còn ở đây, ta có cùng đối tượng khách hàng, cùng sản phẩm,
but we are actually changing it for another factor.
và điều chỉnh giá theo yếu tố khác.
So that would be something we might do, time of day,
Ví dụ như thời gian của một ngày,
nearer to time of event, et cetera.
thời gian gần kề với một sự kiện,...
And this leads us into our next one, which is something
Nó dẫn chúng ta đến khái niệm tiếp theo,
called pricing discrimination.
phân biệt giá.
Now this doesn't sound very nice, because discrimination
Nghe không được hay lắm vì từ phân biệt
is a loaded word.
nghe khá nặng nề.
But pricing discrimination is indeed, in most categories in most jurisdictions,
Nhưng phân biệt giá, trong hầu hết các văn bản quy dịnh quyền hạn,
legal if done in certain ways.
là hợp pháp nếu được thực hiện đúng.
And what it means is we're discriminating
Nó có nghĩa là chúng ta sẽ phân biệt đối xử với
against certain customers based on their willingness to pay.
một nhóm khách hàng dựa vào mức sẵn lòng chi trả của họ.
And so you might say, well I don't believe that.
Bạn có thể sẽ nói là bạn chẳng tin đâu nhé.
Where would that happen.
Nó diễn ra ở đâu thế?
Think about the last time you flew on a plane, or booked into a hotel,
Hãy nghĩ đến lần cuối cùng bạn đi máy bay hay thuê khách sạn
and what do you find.
và bạn nhận thấy gì.
The person next to you paid more or less than you.
Người kế bên trả nhiều hoặc ít tiền hơn bạn.
Not because they got a different seat, but because they
Không phải vì họ ngồi ghế khác, mà bởi vì
showed a different willingness to pay at the time of purchase.
vào thời điểm mua, mức sẵn lòng chi trả của họ khác bạn.
So this then leads us into the topics of whether you
Điều này dẫn đến một vấn đề
are going to be transparent, or whether you are
liệu bạn có muốn việc định giá
going to be opaque with your pricing.
rõ ràng và minh bạch hay không.
So clearly what you have is you move towards discriminatory pricing,
Tiến dần đến phân biệt giá
is you get away from transparency, and towards more opaque offerings.
nghĩa là bạn đang đi từ chỗ minh bạch đến không rõ ràng.
So what's happening there?
Chuyện gì đang diễn ra?
Well the business is trying to make it harder for customers
Các doanh nghiệp thì đang khiến cho khách hàng
to compare pricing offerings.
gặp nhiều khó khăn hơn trong việc so sánh giá cả.
And so they are going to do it by giving you limited access to information
Họ hạn chế khả năng tiếp cận nguồn thông tin
and data where they're able to.
và dữ liệu của bạn.
And we sometimes see this kind of played out in bundled pricing.
Đôi khi ta nhận thấy điều này trong hiện tượng định giá trọn gói.
And that is where people bundle different products, or products
Tức là định giá cả một tổ hợp
and services together.
các sản phẩm và dịch vụ.
And so the unbundling of them would be needed
Bạn cần tính giá từng thứ
to make direct comparisons with what other competitors are offering,
để có thể so sánh với sản phẩm của đối thủ cạnh tranh
or what indeed we are offering to other customers.
hoặc sản phẩm mà chúng ta bán cho khách hàng khác.
So we generally dealt here with transactional pricing,
Chúng ta thường thực hiện định giá giao dịch,
which is a simpler level of pricing then when we get into long term,
một cấp độ định giá cơ bản
or recurring, contracts.
với các hợp đồng dài hạn hoặc định kì.
We haven't dealt with pricing directly in multi-sided markets,
Ta chưa xét đến định giá trong một thị trường hỗn hợp,
but for an introductory level these themes
nhưng ở cấp độ nhập môn này,
will help you advance your understanding a long way.
biết về những chủ đề đó sẽ giúp ích rất nhiều cho bạn trong tương lai.
MUSIC PLAYING
[NHẠC]